Davidson Family Papers WLU.Coll.0113
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Davidson Family Papers
1830-1915
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Davidson, James D. (James Dorman)
Davidson, Mary
Letcher, Greenlee D. (Greenlee Davidson)
WLU.Coll.0113
.5 Linear Feet
Box 1
Folder 1-19
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of papers of Lexington, Virginia lawyer James D. Davidson and his daughter Mary Davidson and includes some correspondence, manuscript and printed poems of James D.Davidson, clippings, and some miscellaneaous papers from the family. James Davidson's printed and handwritten writings in the collection were compiled for his book "A Curiosity in the Chancery and Rhyme and Prose," (N.D., but likely 1876-81). The collection contains detailed genealogy of the Davidson, Greenlee, and McDowell families of Virginia and Kentucky. Other highlights are a typescript paper presented in 1915 by Greenlee Davidson Letcher to the Fortnightly Club of Lexington (Va.) on the life of Capatian Greenlee Davidson, son of James D. Davidson, who died fighting for the Confederacy during the American Civil War, a fragment of a handwritten 19th century recipe book, a small pen and ink drawing on Washington College stationary of the Virginia patriotic doodles and quotations, and a carte de visite photograph of the steamship "City of New York".
Separated Materials
The copy of James D. Davidson's book, "A Curiosity in Chancery and Rhyme and Prose," was removed from this collection and cataloged for our rare book collection housed in Washington and Lee University Special Collections.
Poetry; Manuscripts; Correspondence; Genealogy; Cookbooks; Country lawyers; Davidson, Greenlee; Davidson family; Greenlee family; McDowell family
- Control Folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondences, 1873-1881 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondences, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Notes on liquor laws, temperance, Biblical scripture pertaining to alcohol, and misc. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  General
  Content by James D. Davidson
- Poems and scriptural and general quotations, 1870-1881 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Content in James D. Davidson's hand.
- Poems and Speeches, 1830-1881 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes handwritten and printed material by James D. Davidson. Materials in this folder seem to have been compiled for submission to the publisher (Lexington (Va.) Gazette Printing House)of his book "A Curiosity in Chancery and Rhyme and Prose". Includes a ticket stub for the "Natural Bridge Sunday School Convention Picnic and Music Festival, July 15, 1876".
- Newspaper clippings, 1865-1880 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Includes a complete single edition of "The Commonweath" newspaper of Covington, Ky., July 6, 1876. Clippings of Davidson's writings and interests - Davidson's account of the burial in Hollywood Cemetery (Richmond, Va.) of an artillery soldier, Richard W. Outland, formerly of his son Greenlee's "Letcher Battery" of the Army of Northern Virginia during the American Civil War; humorous description of the hand writing of a number of Lexington's prominent citizens of the 1860s-70s including James D. Davidson.; et al.
- Book - "A Curiosity in Chancery and Ryhme and Prose" by James D. Davidson (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Separated Materials
  This item has been removed frm this colleciton and cataloged within Washington and Lee University's Rare book collection.
- Letters to Mary Davidson, 1884-1885 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Letters written to Mary Davidson on genealogy of the McDowell family. There is one letter regarding genealogy written to Clara (Davidson) Estill, Mary's sister.
  Pickett, Margaret Madison, 1806-1887; Green, Thomas Marshall, 1837-1904
- Genealogy - McDowell, Greenlee, Davidson Families, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Genealogy - McDowell, Greenlee, Davidson Families, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Genealogy - McDowell, Greenlee, Davidson Families, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Genealogy - McDowell Family, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Genealogy - McDowell Family, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Typescript paper on Captain Greenlee Davidson, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Genealogy - Greenlee Family (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Recipe book, 1830-1880 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Handwritten recipes from the Davidson family.
- Newspaper clippings, 1850-1913 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Miscellaneous materials (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Carte de visite of the "City of New York", Virginia patriotic pen and ink drawing (c.1865 - 75?, receipt, Washington College stationary, dried flowers, a chart (table) for finding the day of the week in any month